so we got some soup translations 310mm
he was hurt by me in this way on one
occasion the Buddha was living in guru
allah on the bank of the river near
injera at the root of the Bodhi tree
recently awakened now in that occasion
the Buddha was sitting for seven days
cross-legged experience in the pleasure
of liberation then when those seven days
had passed having emerged from that
composure the Buddha surveyed the world
with his Buddha eye looking around with
his Buddha the Buddha saw beings being
tormented by various torments and being
burnt by various fevers born of passion
you know well inborn delusion he goes
goes without saying here that any fever
they might bother one in any shape or
form on account of anything it has to be
on account of anything it has to be
rooted in these three types of passion
passion
to its pleasure to the displeasure so it
was prolonged pleasure to the world in
displeasure and passion to its ignorance
body has to be rooted in your will and
all delusion so and that's again it's
it's important to emphasize that because
usually when something bothers us that's
when the mind is focused on the object
of that thing so even if you know that
you should be twirling on the
understanding the nature of your
feelings as opposed to what specifically
upsets you you can't help it at a time
because the mind is locked upon the
object of that which is perceived
bothersome so it actually takes effort
to restrain your craving to sort out
this particular thing that's all that's
bothering you instead of instead of
stepping back and trying to learn from
the or trying to investigate and discern
the entire situation the nature of the
entire situation because that's the
whole point so knowing that that
whatever whatever might be causing you
any type of fever that's bothering you
knowing that it has to be rooted in
either passion ill-will or delusion so
it has to be rooted in your attitude not
in the object of thing that's bothering
you that's the that's that emphasis
that's there again as I said it makes
sense and and people understand it in
theory but in practice actually takes
effort the first restraint trying to
deal with this particular thing that's
affecting you and then you'll practice
understanding the nature of things
but actually understanding the nature of
things is fundamentally dealing with
anything including this particular thing
that might be bothering you so when the
would have seen the cause of this it
says here at that moment he uttered the
following this world having become
tormented afflicted by
contact speaks of disease as self so on
the basis of passion on the basis of
action rooted in passion all this
torment arises when I can't back torment
you are the one being pressured for as
the buddha as the translation is as
contact contacted pasa means means means
exercise pressure over you contact you
so you left out of it
so having having been tormented you're
pressured and and then what that whole
situation is it's a form of disease yet
for you is the one thing you know and
you speak of it as self thank was for
the same whatever one conceives it is
otherwise than that in other words on
the basis of this passion on the basis
of this pressure whatever you assumed
whatever you assumed to be acting two
words to be trying to deal with
fundamentally it's always otherwise than
that and that means that even if you
assume things to be this way they are so
to speak the fact that you give priority
to that assumption the fact that you
give priority to the unquestioned basis
of passion for your action you took our
for granted so because of that whatever
you conceive works otherwise than that
being otherwise the world is attached to
be
Aflac I feel afflicted by being he
delights in being so that'sthat's the
point here I'm trying to make when when
the foundation of your thoughts of your
intention is passion aversion or
delusion that's already a form of
perversion in regard to the reason state
the phenomenon in regard to the reason
experienced as a whole because of that
perversion even if you think along the
right lines of the experience as a whole
you are not undoing the perversion which
means whichever way you conceive it it's
otherwise than that in other words
you're conceiving makes things wrong
even if you try to think it rightly and
that's like in a case of petitioner who
can be familiar I mean can know by heart
all the suitors and even understand them
on the level but still remain at Aegina
is because the certain basis of passion
your will and delusion has not been
undone they're still being held for
granted has still been acting out oh and
that's what wouldn't means here mmm
so whatever one conceives each other
within that in other words the world for
you becomes the world of your conceiving
on the basis of your passion and that's
what things that first restraint that I
said in regard to things that say
something specific torments you or
something there's some particular fever
bothering you account of something that
upsets you that that in itself it's
already a product of that as what I said
it's the base of whatever comment it's
on the basis of passion so that in
itself is already a product of your
concealing you conceive that to be the
problem so that's why it takes that
restraint first to stop acting
habitually out of what you think the
problem is because that's how you keep
up a trading the very
savings that are making you suffer in
the first place so looking at the
general nature of things as opposed to
particular things it's the first step
but if you don't do that you're going to
be acting out of what you conceive
problem to be which means you are
conceiving this to be problem or not
problem in other words you are
conceiving it being on the basis of the
mind affected by passion it will and
illusion and that's what the Buddha means yet
and that's what the Buddha means yet
afflicted by being sorry being otherwise
the world is attached to being so
whatever one conceives it is otherwise
than that being otherwise the world is
attached to that being in other words
that's that's your world what you
conceive it to be that is the threshold
of being for you
that's what barber palette and bhava
which stands for being is it's it's
something a petition is responsible for
something everybody is responsible for
to different extent and that's why that
being can be undone without necessarily
needing things to disappear and be
destroyed around you because that's not
what the painting is the being is you're
conceiving on top of the recent
experience as a whole so having
conceived it things are otherwise than
that in other words your assumption of
that being means it's always going to be
secondary to the reason phenomena so
it's always otherwise than that
even if it's the same thing being
otherwise you assume or rather you are
bound with that being that you have
assumed and so you are emotionally bound
as well and because you're bound by your
afflicted by it because you're bound by
it you delight in it you rejoice in it
and so in other words that's all you
have your assumption of being is what
being is for you because further says
whatever it rejoices in that is fearful
whatever you rejoices in that is fearful
whatever it fears that is suffering so
by being bound by the assumption that
product of your conceiving that product
of your passion ill-will and delusion
you start developing attitudes towards
that being they bind you towards the
nature that the world sorry don't away
from the nature of of the arisen
phenomenon so then you will be
delighting it you'll be rejoicing it
you'll be fearing it and any form of
these attitudes that are rooted in this
form of us in this in this type of
conceiving those that because of that
those attitudes are the the suffering
for you and that's then the Buddha goes
further but the holy life is lived for
the abandoning of being so abandoning of
that we choose you to be now it's
important to point out here when I say
assume to be doesn't mean there is a
hidden reality behind that is the
reality that you have that's why the
acceptance in a way is not acting out of
it the restraint and the acceptance is
the first attitude because kaputo Jinnah
the assumed being is all that's in front
of him sure he can now undo that
assumption and find something more
wholesome to be in front of him and
that's how you undo the being and
replace it with with non be with
knowledge with cessation and so on with
with this passion but if that being
hasn't been undone and now you think
about something like things in
themselves that are independent of that
being well that's done on the basis of
your steel being and that's that's the
problem when people start assuming oh
there is a this is not real there is a
reality behind this failing to see that
they are thought of reality behind is on
the basis of this reality which means in
it in as much as it can sort of presents
itself as pure and wholesome it won't be
because it's on the basis
of the perversion that the Buddha just
described here perversion caused by
passion the version caused by it will end
the version caused by it will end
illusion the results in conceiving that
end result an attitude of assuming this
to be that's it doesn't need to be more
specific than that
so whatever further then you assume
you'll be equally assuming it to be so
even when you think about the pure
reality behind your appearances you end
up assuming that to be on account of
disappearance that you already perverted
with passion and so on so that's what
the holy life is not about finding the
alternate clear reality that will kind
of result in freedom from all the
problems it's basically about undoing
the assumption of anything any form of
being you undo that assumption and
that's what if because you do the being
you and do undo any form of attitude the
world of being you you undo any form of
fear pressure engagement with it and
actually there there goes I think the
very the next verse says that says those
ascetics and brahmins who speak about
liberation of being by being all of them
are not liberated from being and that's
exactly the point I was making so all of
those ascetics and Brahmins they speak
about the divine order the reality
behind this or well even Aparna many
people use the ban in a mystical sense
or some sort of mystical reality behind
the appearances that you need to
discover through your ascetic or
whatever practices you might be doing
failing to see that no matter where you
arrived it's going to be another pain on
the basis of perversion of your being
that you already have so that's what
exactly what it will means here whoever
speaks about liberation of being by
being that person is not liberating from
liberated from being I say although and
those ascetics and Brahmins who speak
about the escape from being by non being
all of them have not escaped being I say
and that's the other way when you now
see the being is a problem and then you
just denied but denial of your
assumption is on the basis of your
assumption so first group
replaces mom being with another being
you know find a better being the other
person tries to undo this being by
denying it saying oh there is no being
there is no reality there is nothing is
real everything is an illusion and by
denying the assumption they think they
found a way of out of assumption but
again any attitude towards assumption
binds you to the assumption bind you to
the being and that's exactly says I
think oh yeah because of assuming this
suffering arises so the world for
assumption is oppa Donna so because of
this assumption suffering arises that's
it no because of this because of that
because this happened this didn't happen
no because you assumed in the first
place all these things that happen or
might happen or didn't happen will
affect you so trying to replace it won't
work because it doesn't undo the
assumption trying to denied equally
futile so with the destruction of all
Assumption there won't be any arising of
suffering see this world afflicted by
various kind of ignorance beings
delighting in what is I'm not free from
being for whatever ways of being there
are everywhere as a whole all those ways
of being are impermanent suffering of
the nature to change and that's exactly
what we have been talking about seeing
this in this way as it is with right
understanding craving for being is
abandoned and one does not delight in
not being either so you stop craving but
that which the basis of your assumption
offers you as I open up this whole thing
saying something bothers you you think
that particular thing must be dealt with
that's all in the form of your craving
it feeds the assumption that's on the
basis of that craving the fees
assumption that in return provides a
basis for that further craving so your
craving for you know questioning the
validity of the being you're basically
trying to deal with output being
presented you with so craving will be a
and if one starts seeing things without
understanding and also it would delight
in non-being trying to get rid of the
whole being in front of you which
includes the things that have arisen on
their own that kind of provide basis for
your assumption for your conceiving as
we discussed so you stop delighting in
that as well so with the complete
destruction of craving there is the
remainder less fading away cessation and
abana for this extinguished monk with
non assuming there isn't any further
being he is conquered mara victorious in
battle he's he's such a one who has
overcome all ways of being so that's it